<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | MEL Lab</title>
    <link>https://calandryll.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://calandryll.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 19:44:09 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://calandryll.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://calandryll.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harmful Algal Blooms</title>
      <link>https://calandryll.github.io/project/habs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 19:44:09 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://calandryll.github.io/project/habs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Phytoplankton are of fundamental importance in the aquatic environment. Utilizing light, carbon dioxide, and various nutrients to photosynthetically produce biomass which provides the energy and material for the base of the food web. There are several thousands of extant algal species in the fresh and marine environment. In the marine environment alone, there are estimated 5,000 species of which 300 species are known to cause harmful algal blooms (HABs) where under certain conditions algal cells may proliferate into millions of cells per liter. Many HAB species produce toxins that can kill fish or other aquatic organisms or accumulate in fish or other organism’s tissues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the freshwater environment, the cyanobacteria are the most widespread and problematic algal taxa. The cyanobacteria are found in three distinct morphological groups: unicellular, either as solitary or aggregated colonies (i.e., Microcystis); differentiated filaments containing nitrogen fixing cells called heterocysts (i.e., Anabaena); and undifferentiated, nonheterocystous filaments (i.e., Oscillatoria). Nuisance and potentially toxic blooms of cyanobacteria generally occur in eutrophic or hypereutrophic waters. These blooms are influenced by pools of both nitrogen and phosphorus, coupled with the ability by many species for nitrogen fixation, blooms formation may last for prolonged periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recreational waters, cyanobacteria can cause problems by decreasing dissolved oxygen concentrations during die off that may result in fish kills. In addition, cyanobacteria may produce taste and odor compounds that affect the taste of fish and can be a nuisance to those living or recreating on effected water bodies. Under favorable conditions, some cyanobacteria strains produce toxins that can cause illness and death in humans and animals. Cyanobacteria may produce one or several types of cyanotoxins that affect the liver (hepatotoxins), nervous system (neurotoxins) and skin (dermatoxins).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cyanobacterial harmful algal blooms (cyanoHABs) are a growing concern in the global arena for their potential impact water quality, ecosystem services and human health. Increased eutrophication and climate change have resulted in the proliferation, intensification and prolonging of cyanoHABs around the world (Cook et al., 2019). Formation of blooms are regulated by water temperature, light availability and trophic conditions. Typically, cyanoHABs favor warm temperatures, high nutrient loads and low-flow conditions, conditions seen in many of the lakes and ponds of Delaware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blooms may vary in species composition and toxin production over time and within a water body. Cyanobacteria can also be distributed as surface scums (e.g., Microcystis), at a particular depth (e.g., Planktothrix rubescens), or throughout the entire water column (e.g., Planktothrix sp.). Distribution of cyanobacteria can be affected by winds, rainfall, and lake turnover, in addition, some species can regulate buoyancy, allowing for vertical movement in the water column. These factors are important in understanding blooms as the absence of a surface bloom is not indicative of bloom presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Color is also not indicative of bloom occurrence. While the name “blue-green algae” is a colloquial term for cyanobacteria, the color range of cyanobacteria can range from brown, white, black purple, red, green, or a combination. For example, Cylindrospermopsis may form blooms that are brown in color and may appear as suspended sediment. Blooms that appear green in color may be mistaken for non-harmful blooms of green algae. Proper distinguishing of cyanobacterial blooms is through processed satellite data, microscopic examination, or use of other cyanobacteria screening techniques (i.e., molecular methods, cyanotoxin field kits).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to toxin production, cyanoHABs can have negative ecosystem health impacts and can raise concerns for drinking water, recreational water use and animals. While large blooms can produce excessive dissolved oxygen, when the bloom crashes it can decrease dissolved oxygen resulting in non-toxin related fish kills. Many cyanobacteria also produce taste and odor compounds that can affect the taste of fish and drinking water. Additionally, the foul smell produced by these blooms can also be a nuisance to those living and recreating on the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cyanobacteria can produce a wide variety of secondary metabolites including peptides, polyketides, and alkaloids. These secondary metabolites can cause illness and potentially fatal in humans and animals, and may attack the liver, nerves, or skin. Some of the common cyanotoxins include microcystin, nodularin, saxitoxin, anatoxin-a, and cylindrospermopsin. Cyanotoxins can also bioaccumulate within the aquatic food web and may pose threat across all trophic levels. Many of the state-managed ponds have suffered from seasonal or episodic algal blooms that include potentially toxic cyanobacterial species. Microcystin has been found in low concentrations in several ponds but surveys of pond users indicated no evidence of direct toxic impacts to humans, pets, or wildlife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are an estimated 5000 extant species of algae in the marine environment. Among those species, approximately 300 are known to cause HABs, and like their freshwater counterpart, may produce toxins that can kill fish other marine organisms or accumulate in fish or shellfish tissue. Eutrophication of Delaware’s inland bays (DIB) has increased over the last several decades, with most of the nutrient input from agricultural and urban sources (Price, 1998; Sallade and Sims, 1997). Several harmful or potentially harmful species have been occurring frequently in DIB, with many occurring in the dead-end canals. Among those species are the dinoflagellates: Dinophysis spp., Gyrodinium instriatum, Karlodinium veneficum, and Prorocentrum minimum and several marine raphidophyte species: Heterosigma akashiwo, Chattonella subsalsa, Fibrocapsa japonica, and Viridilobus marinus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distribution of algae in the marine environment is influenced by a wide range of processes that include circulation, light and nutrient availability, as well as biological interactions. Algal dynamics is often driven by small to mesoscale processes where the water column is often stratified and areas where strong vertical density gradients occur, e.g., fjords, coastal lagoons, polar regions, and dead-end canals. This stratification can produce favorable conditions for the algae leading to large scale blooms, it has been observed that many large HAB species form in subsurface thin layers during bloom conditions . Algal growth has been classically measured as a whole-community response, with the use of chlorophyll as a proxy for abundance. However, this measurement has two presumptions: the community is taxonomically identical, and the community measurement adequately represents the dominant taxa.
Similar to cyanoHABs, color is not indicative of a bloom occurrence. The term “red-tide” is a misnomer as color can range from green, brown, red, or “mahogany”. Proper distinguishing of blooms is through processed satellite data, microscopic examination, or use of other screening techniques (e.g., molecular methods).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In humans, toxicity can be caused by ingestion of contaminated seafood, skin contact, or inhalation of aerosolized toxins or noxious compounds. In food borne illness, HAB toxins are bioaccumulated, often without harming the vector marine organism that ingested the toxin and transfers up the food web to humans. Toxic effects are typically observed when the toxin producing species is at high concentration, however poisoning via seafood can also occur by highly toxic algae at lower concentrations. Indirect effects from toxin production have consequences on human well-being in terms of their socioeconomic impact and costs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microbial Source Tracking</title>
      <link>https://calandryll.github.io/project/microbial-source-tracking/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://calandryll.github.io/project/microbial-source-tracking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One measurable type of potential human-related water pollution is fecal bacteria.  These bacteria may derive from humans, various domesticated animals, i.e. dogs, cats, cows, etc. or from wild animals.  Bacteria within the genus Enterococcus has been widely adopted to indicate the presence of fecal matter from warm-blooded animals in 305(b) monitoring efforts.  Delaware has risk-based numeric criteria for Primary Contact Recreation (PCR) and Secondary Contact Recreation (SCR) in freshwater and saltwater “determined by the Department (DNREC) to be of non-wildlife origin based on best scientific judgment using available information”.  Important among the limitations of the Enterococcus test is that it does not differentiate as to what type of animal the detected bacteria are from.  It could be any mix of warm-blooded animal types that might be in the watershed – i.e. mammals and birds, domestic and wildlife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these Enterococcus criteria are generally recognized to be protective of human health and the continuation of routine monitoring of waters is necessary to track status and trends, this test does not help in locating sources of bacterial contamination, which may be abatable.  A supplemental, complimentary addition to the existing monitoring format is needed to facilitate where to apply pollution control practices and maximize the frugal utilization of the increasingly scarce resources available to bring about the environmental improvements intended under the CWA, such that waters meet standards criteria and attain designated uses, for example, PCR, SCR, fish, aquatic life and wildlife and harvestable shellfish waters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecosystem services of coastal waters are important for community health, tourism and aquaculture. However, our coastal waters are under constant threats from pollution, land use change and increasing severe hydrologic events including coastal and areal flooding.  Inherent in a coastal healthy ecosystem is a lack of pollution from anthropogenic influences, a tolerance for flooding without additional pollution and a resilient natural biota.  A main threat to coastal ecosystem health is the introduction of fecal material from humans, pets and livestock. As waste material these concerns are primary for human health, but also of concern is that infectious materials can be spread between species. As such, the continual monitoring of waterways for fecal material is inherent to statewide monitoring efforts. If bacterial loads are raised in waterways, tourism can be shut down and aquaculture can be impacted. As such the spread of bacteria in the environment is of great concern for the continued maintenance of a healthy coastal ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the state of Delaware, the Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control (DNREC) Department of Water, located in the Office of Environmental Protection, produces data for the monitoring of waterway health. The DNREC Department of Watershed Stewardship, located in the Office of Natural Resources, is responsible for enacting policies and actual management of watersheds. While the data produced regarding microbial impairment of waterway health can be acted on by stakeholders for conservation and ecosystem service health priorities, the watershed-level impacts of waterway impairment are often not able to be acted upon, as the data collected by standard required measurements are not explicit enough to enact policy level enforcement by the Department of Watershed Stewardship. Our project seeks to gain detailed data on the microbial impairment of coastal waters in Delaware, tracking the sources of microbial input from watershed areas, in powerful enough form to compel the offices within DNREC, and potentially as large as the EPA, to reconsider the practices of waterway monitoring and policy enforcement regarding potential microbial pollution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
